Guide to the Rose Weiner Papers ALBA.116
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Rose Weiner Papers
1933-1995
ALBA.116
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
0.25 linear feet (1 box)
Rose Weiner (1908-1995) was a nurse for the American Medical Bureau for Spanish Democracy during the Spanish Civil War. This collection consists of letters, documents, and photocopied photographs from Weiner’s personal scrapbook.
Weiner, Rose
Provenance
The Rose Weiner Papers were separated from a scrapbook donated to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Gerrie Karasik in 1996. The scrapbook came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Rose Weiner (1908-1995) was born in Lyubar, Russia into a Jewish family. As a child Rose experienced the harsh conditions of the Russian Revolution and counter-revolution while she, her mother and siblings awaited word from her father who had already migrated to the United States. On September 25, 1921, Rose and her family arrived at the Port of New York before moving to Milwaukee.
In order to continue her schooling, Weiner moved back to New York and attended the Montefiore Hospital School of Nursing from 1929-1932. After graduation, Rose accepted a position at Montefiore Hospital. In March 1937 she decided sailed to Spain as an American medical volunteer in support of the Loyalist forces in the Spanish Civil War. Weiner worked as a floor nurse in a convalescent hospital, of which she was soon given charge. She then spent several months working on the front lines before taking charge of a surgical hospital. During her last six months in Spain, Weiner served as chief nurse of a 1,500-bed surgical and medical hospital.
Rose returned to New York in 1939 and continued work at Montefiore Hospital. Although she applied for nursing positions in the American Red Cross, Army Nurse Corps and War Manpower Commission during WWII, Weiner was never granted any of these positions, on the grounds that she did not meet physical requirements. Soon after her attempts to serve in the war, Weiner left Montefiore and began work for New York City as a Public Health Nurse. Meanwhile, she worked toward her Bachelor of Science degree at Hunter College. Weiner later worked as a school nurse until she retired in the 1970s.
Scope and Content Note
Series I, Correspondence, 1942-1944; 1991, contains letters written to Weiner from the American Red Cross, Army Nurse Corps and War Manpower Commission in the early 1940s, rejecting her applications to serve as a nurse in World War II. Also included is Weiner's reply to the American Red Cross, reiterating her qualifications. This series also includes letters written to Weiner's niece in the 1991 from two of Weiner's friends, both of whom had worked with Weiner.
Series II, Subject Files, 1933-1995, contains Weiner's certificate of U.S. citizenship, official documents from her service in the Spanish Civil War, and certificates that registered her for nursing in New York. Also included are photocopies of a Weiner family scrapbook, from which the documents in this collection were separated. [Photographs separated from the scrapbook can be found in the Weiner Photograph Collection, ALBA PHOTO #116.]
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically within each series.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
I. Correspondence, 1942-1944; 1991.
II. Subject Files, 1933-1995.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Toby Jensky and Philip Schachter Papers, ALBA #55
Mildred Rackley Simon, ALBA #97
Edward K. Barsky Papers, ALBA #125
Fredericka Martin Papers, ALBA #1
Frances Patai Papers, ALBA #131
Separated Material
Photographs from Rose Weiner scrapbook have been separated to the Rose Weiner Photograph Collection (ALBA Photo #116). For further information related to the scope and contents of the photograph collection see, The Guide to the Rose Weiner Photograph Collection.
Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy.; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy.; North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy.; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV.; Weiner, Rose; Correspondence.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Hospitals.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Participation, American.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |x Women.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1942-1944; 1991.
  - Beard, Mary to Weiner, Rose, Aug 19, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Byron, Rose to Karasik, Gerrie and Len, Feb 12, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hall, Ruth to Mary Weiner, May 13, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rosenbaum, Della, to Karasik, Gerrie, Apr 22, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Walson, Colonel M.C. to Weiner, Rose, Sep 8, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Weiner, Rose to Beard, Mary, Sep 24, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1933-1995.
  - Certificate of U.S. Citizenship, Feb 6, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Certificates for Nursing (U.S.), 1932, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Certificate of Service in Spain and Letter of Thanks, Nov 1938-Dec 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook: Photocopy, undated, ca.1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Real Estate Transaction, Aug 30, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Weiner, Rose: Obituary, Dec 1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)